Tov today's דף daf is קס"ד, kof samech daled, we're ahead so
we're picking up on the top of קס"ד kof samech daled עמוד
ב'. amud bet. And we basically and we have said that you
are not allowed to have two blank lines between the signatures and
the and the last line of the of the of the שטר
shtar because if you have two blank lines meaning what we do
number one is we understand that people are going to not write
directly underneath they're going to give some space and they're going to
write you know so whatever יעקב בן יצחק Yaakov ben Yitzchak עד
aid here fine but then that leaves an opportunity for somebody to
sneak in a line here and say something new. So the first
principle is אין למידין משיטה אחרונה ayn lamedin mishitah achronah but then
we say alright fine but that's what if there's a space of
two blank lines the שטר shtar is פסול pasul because then somebody
can sneak in two lines and you won't learn from the last
line but you'll learn from the second to last line. So the
גמרא Gemara now is going to start with that in mind and
let's look at the question in
the
גמרא. Gemara. It would be
a line and a
half is enough to significantly affect the content. Right but the point
is you're not למידין משיטה אחרונה. lamedin mishitah achronah.
Yeah
but but the half line
oh so a line and a half let me make it clear
line and a half means that this height is 1.5 like high.
Yes meaning תוספות Tosafos has a possibility that a line and a
half meant that you know that the actual שטר shtar that that
the עדים eidim sort of signed here עד
עדים aid eidim signed here and that what you can now do
is add like a line and a half like that right that's
what that's what תוספות Tosafos sort of thought suggests maybe it means
but then תוספות Tosafos says no like in that type of a
case we would just presume that you would not learn from the
line above the עדים eidim and the line sort of to get
you know along the עדים eidim but yes but no the line
and a half the best way to read it is is that
means the height it's the height of a line and a half
so are we afraid that somebody is going to sneak in two
small lines or are we going to say look we're not going
to be afraid that they'll make it obvious so we don't have
to be afraid somebody's going to do that. Okay, תא שמע tashma
come and hear הרחיק את העדים שתי שיטים פסול Hirchik et haeidim
shtei shitim pasul and it's pretty clear from all the evidence that
that's what we're talking about the column height as they would say
okay or the whatever the row height I guess anyway if you
have them two lines away from the end of the document it
is invalid הא שיטה ומחצה כשר ha shitah umachtzah kasher so a
line and a half it's כשר kasher אימא סיפא aima seifa שיטה
אחת כשר shitah achat kasher
if you have it only one line distant it's כשר kasher שיטה
אחת הוא דכשר הא שיטה ומחצה פסול shitah achat hu d'kasher ha
shitah umachtzah pasul so okay only one line distance is כשר kasher
a line and a half would be פסול pasul אלא מהא ליכא
למשמע מינה ela meha leika lishmi minah classic גמרא Gemara you can't
you know you don't know what the middle case is so we
cannot infer it one way or the other
okay so now the גמרא Gemara says like this אלא מאי הוי
עלה ela mai hava lah
what was the conclusion? תא שמע tashma come and hear דתניא detanya
הרחיק את העדים שתי שיטים מן הכתב פסול hirchik et haeidim shtei
shitim min haksav pasul if it's two lines separate it's פסול pasul
פחות מכאן pachot mikan so this is much better this doesn't have
you know a different number it just says anything less than two
כשר kasher okay so that's our conclusion anything less than two is
כשר kasher because then it'll be obvious if somebody tries to get
two lines in there that they inserted it and we're not afraid
that somebody's going to try to pull the wool over our eyes.
Now here we have a very interesting הלכה halachah היו ארבעה או
חמישה עדים חותמין על השטר hayu arbaah o chamishah eidim chotmin al
hashtar
let's say there was four or five witnesses signed on a שטר
shtar it was more than the requisite two ונמצא אחד מהם קרוב
או פסול v'nimtza achad mehem karov o pasul
and one of them was invalid either a קרוב karov or a
גזלן gazlan or something תתקיים עדות בשאר titkayem eidut bashtar the rest
of the עדים eidim can be good עדים eidim
and why is that relevant for our discussion now it's a very
interesting הלכה halachah which we'll get back to but why is it
relevant for our discussion now because of the next line and some
claim this was already the context of the first line מסייע ליה
לחזקיה וספורטיסיא דאמר חזקיה מלאו בקרובים כשר mesayeia lei l'Chizkiyah v'sportiseya d'amar
Chizkiyah miluo bikrovim kasher
if you filled the שטר shtar with that the white space with
קרובים bikrovim it's כשר kasher ואל תתמה v'altitmah do not be astounded
שהרי אויר סוכה פסול בשלושה סכך פסול פוסל
בארבעה sheharei avir sukah pasul bishloshah schach pasul posel b'arbaah so that
came from nowhere okay if you have אויר avir in a סוכה
sukah three טפחים t'fachim is a problem but if you fill it
with let's say metal bars you've made it כשר kasher until you
have four טפחים t'fachim of not כשר kasher סכך schach so what
the heck are we talking about here here's what we're talking about
okay base Okay, here we have our שטר, shtar, here we have
our עדים, edim, and I was not listening to what the what
the rabbi said and I basically put my עדים edim like three
lines away from the thing. Okay, so what am I going to
do? Oh, no problem. What I'll do is I'll just get more
עדים edim to sign above and to fill in the white space,
so it's not going to be more than a, you know, a
two-line gap. But let's say those עדים edim I get to fill
it in are not כשר kosher עדים. edim. Let's say they're פסול
עדים. pasul edim Okay. So will that be okay? And the logic
should be: wait, it was פסול pasul with the white space. The
white space is like the air of the סוכה. sukkah. It was
it was a פסול pasul שטר shtar with that white space. You
filled in the פסול pasul שטר shtar with something פסול, pasul with
פסול pasul, עדים. edim. Okay. How is filling in that פסול pasul
white space with פסול pasul עדים edim. going to make it כשר?
kasher? So the the analogy, of course this is completely just an
analogy is, well think about a סוכה. sukkah. Now what's the story
with a סוכה? sukkah? The story with a סוכה sukkah is the
following: If you've got a סוכה, sukkah, let's see if I can
try my 3D drawings, okay. Let's say you've got a סוכה, sukkah,
let's start like this, it's only got three walls, okay. Here's your
סוכה, sukkah, here's your סכך, sechach, okay. This is one you know
what, I think bird's eye view will probably be easier although I
like to show off my 3D abilities. Okay, it's only got three
walls in your סוכה, sukkah, okay? Now, if you have a gap
of three טפחים tfachim of air in your סכך, sechach,
okay this is סכך sechach and this is סכך. sechach. If this
is three טפחים, tfachim, okay, then that means that the סכך sechach
is not seen as continuous. So you have only a half a
סוכה sukkah here and a half a סוכה sukkah here. This is
a gap, okay? It's not a continuous סוכה. sukkah. But this סוכה
sukkah only has two walls, and this סוכה sukkah only has two
walls. So the סוכה sukkah is פסול, pasul okay? If you had
the gap this way, this half would be פסול pasul, but this
half would be כשר kasher because this half would still have three
walls. Okay, but that breaks the סוכה sukkah into two, it's no
longer a continuous sort of entity. Okay, and therefore it's פסול. pasul
But if you went ahead and instead of having air what you
had here was פסול סכך, pasul sechach, because it's actually something, it's
not a gap, then it's continuous. And because it's continuous, it's a
כשר kasher סוכה sukkah until you actually were to get four טפחים.
tfachim. Four טפחים tfachim then it would be defined as like its
own section in the middle, okay. But because it's something, it's not
an opening, it creates greater sense of a continuity. And if it's
four
טפחים, tfachim, four טפח tefach space is its own space, okay, so
then it's like then it would be a break and then you'd
have like three entities, you know, one entity, two entities, three and
then it wouldn't be continuous, it would be פסול. pasul. But three
טפחים tfachim is כשר, kasher, only four טפחים tfachim is פסול. pasul.
So if you fill that white space, as it were, with something
bad, you've actually made the סוכה sukkah more כשר. kosher. All right,
so the idea here is that if you fill this white space
with פסול pasul. עדים, edim you've actually made it more כשר. kasher.
Now again, you could say that that's just like a metaphor and
an analogy, like don't be astounded, that's what he says אל תתמה.
al tithameh. That's absurd! It was פסול pasul when it was white
and now you're putting something bad in? Yeah, we have that other
places. There's no real direct analogy, obviously this is completely different logics
that dictates in the two places. The logic here is like I
said, that if it's not if it's air, it creates a greater
gap between the two entities than if it's פסול סכך. pasul sechach.
Here the logic is that if it's white space, it could be
forged. If it's not white space, it can't be forged even if
it's פסול pasul עדים, edim, right? So there's a good logic that
dictates in each case why filling it with something bad makes it
better, but it's not the same logic, right? You're not you're not
really learning from one to the other. תוספות Tosafot in order to
make it, you know, make say that it is saying something of
significance, says don't like what we're learning from סוכה sukkah is we're
not going to make a גזירה. gezeirah. We're not going to say
oh, you know, we won't allow three טפחים tfachim of bad סכך
sechach because it'll come to a case of allowing three טפחים tfachim
of air. So here too we're not going to say we won't
allow פסול pasul עדים edim, because it'll come to a case of
allowing for a blank space. So making it address a rabbinic concern.
But anyway, but the point that doesn't seem to be the real
חזקיה Chizkiyah point. חזקיה's Chizkiyah real point more just seems to be,
it seems strange that you take something that's that's blank and you
fill it with something bad and filling it with something bad makes
it better rather than worse, but that's the logic. Here it removes
the sense of a gap and a discontinuity and here it prevents
the ability from
from forging the document and from adding פסול pasul lines. I should
say that there's a fascinating תשובה teshuvah the ריב"ד, Rivad, I know
about this because like when my brother and I went to Israel
when we were teenagers, like in 17 or whatever, and we finally
got like so we were there in Israel whatever, we got our
תפילין tefillin checked and my brother's תפילין tefillin actually had like a
word repeated, you know, it was sort of like... It was sort
of like it said on one line ושננתם לבניך v'shinantam l'vanecha and
the next line said לבניך ודברת בם. l'vanecha v'dibarta bam. Okay, so
anyway, so whatever, he had to get new תפילין, tefillin, but I
was doing some research and I found this תשובה teshuva of the
ראב"ד, Ravad, and the ראב"ד Ravad says that if you actually have
a doubled word in תפילין, tefillin, it's not פסול, pasul and he
says ואל תתמה v'al titma and he uses this comparison: if it
was white space it would be כשר, kasher, so if you filled
it with a different word, it's also going to be כשר. kasher.
So it's a quite interesting use of this idea. But anyway, I
don't know what the logic is there at all, but okay. Anyway,
but this is the ruling, okay? Now, so that's probably what the
חזקיה's Chizkiah statement—why we quoted the—I mean why we quoted the whatever—when
it starts with saying right here, הרחיק את העדים שתי שיטין מן
הכתב פסול פסול פשטן כשר, Hirchik es ha'edim shtei shitin min haktav
pasul pasul pshatan kasher, היו ארבעה וחמישה עדים חתומים על השטר ונמצא
אחד מהם קרוב או פסול. hayu arba'ah vechamishah edim chatumim al hashtar
venimtza echad mehem karov o pasul. So some read that as an
independent statement. Oh, by the way, here's a הלכה halacha that if
you have multiple signatures and some are פסול, pasul, the שאר shear
is still כשר. kasher. But תוספות Tosafot says it really makes more
sense that that's a continuation of the previous line. If it's too
many lines separate, it's invalid, but you can fill it with פסול
pasul, עדים edim because even if some of the עדים edim are
פסול, pasul, it is still going to be כשר. kasher. Okay, now,
the question is, why is it כשר? kasher? Whatever happened to the
what? Yeah, that's me I think, I'm sorry, I think my texts
are going. Okay, so the question is, why is it כשר? kasher?
Whatever happened to the ruling that by a פסול, pasul, you know,
that normally we say that if you have a group of עדים
edim and some of them are פסול, pasul, they're all פסול, pasul,
right? נמצא אחד מהם קרוב או פסול, nimtza echad mehem karov o
pasul, they're all פסול. pasul. So תוספות Tosafot basically says that the
reason is because even when עדים edim come to a בית דין
beit din
to testify, right, let's say you have a group of עדים edim
that come to בית דין beit din to testify, one of them
is פסול, pasul, that's only after we said all of you are
coming to the בית דין beit din to testify. So we say
to you like, well, you know, or you're coming to the בית
דין beit din to tell us I don't know what you saw.
So we say like, well, are you coming here to officially register
your testimony, right? Are you here to? And only when you are
officially there to, you know, to go through, yes, I'm here as
a witness, we go through, we swear you in—okay, we don't swear
you in, whatever we do, we scare you, we go through a
whole process. So that process makes you a witness. And then if
all of you become witnesses through that process that you tell us
that you're here to testify and we accept you in that process
or whatever, then we've got a group of witnesses, one of them
is פסול, pasul, we're going to throw it all out. He says,
but iron—now of course what you and I would think is, anybody
who's signing a שטר shtar is essentially saying I'm here to testify,
that's an act of testifying, right? And maybe because we say it's
כמי שנחקרה עדותם בבית דין, k'mi shenichkra edutam b'veit din, all the
more so, your signing a שטר shtar is like your testimony's already
been received. But the funny thing is that because there's not like
a בית דין beit din there accepting your testimony, all there is
is you and your, you know, pen and your שטר, shtar, right,
we can actually say that we are going to claim—I mean again,
I don't know how we know—but we're going to claim that since
you were פסול, pasul, you were not intentionally doing it, right? You
did not mean to do it to testify. So why did you
do it? Well, maybe you did it to fill up the white
space. Or maybe you did it, and this is interesting because the
רמ"א Rema records this practice, the גמרא Gemara actually records this practice,
but the רמ"א Rema records that they actually would do this למעשה.
l'maaseh. Maybe you did it as just a way of showing like,
you know, as a כבוד, kavod, you know, they're always looking at
weddings for more כיבודים, kibbudim, right? So why don't we just let
more people sign the שטר? shtar? Okay, or you did it, meaning
either they gave you a כיבוד kibbud or, the way the גמרא
Gemara makes it more sound, you were doing it to show to
give כבוד kavod to the חתן וכלה chosson v'kallah if it was
let's say a כתובה, ketubah, okay? You wanted to like, you know,
be part of the activity and sign your name. Of course it
doesn't exactly explain it when it's like a, you know, it's just
a—it's just like ראובן Reuven borrowed a thousand dollars from שמעון, Shimon,
what's the כבוד? kavod? But you know, maybe the כבוד kavod is,
I don't know, you're allow—maybe you're doing a כיבוד kibbud for me,
you're letting me sign a שטר, shtar, means you show that you
care about me, I don't know. Okay, but we can imagine somehow
that you were doing it for some other reason, and therefore we
don't view it as an act of testimony. Now again, it's bizarre
because you would say the signing is implicitly putting your name to
something testifying to something. It could be ironically,
even putting aside the question of what motivated you, it could be
ironically that because there's not a formal act of בית דין beit
din accepting it, because the הלכה halacha is signatures on a שטר
shtar become like they're accepted in בית דין, beit din, that it's
almost like
by definition,
if you—how should I say
this?—if this signature would not make it, would make it a not
valid שטר, shtar, then somehow it never becomes כמי שנחקרה עדותם בבית
דין. k'mi shenichkra edutam b'veit din. Like, it only gets the status
of being testimony because it becomes part of—it's like circ—you know what
I'm saying? It's sort of like circular. It only becomes valid as
testimony because it's recognized as part of the שטר, shtar, but if
it can never be val—like if it can never be... Meaning in
the case by a real live בית דין, beis din, it gets
accepted as testimony because the court accepted it. Here it gets accepted
by testimony because הלכה halacha recognizes it as עדות, edus, but הלכה
halacha can't recognize a פסול pasul עד ed as עדות, edus, so
somehow it automatically gets excluded and in a case would be an
interesting test case would be let's say everybody who signed really intended
to testify. They didn't even think they were related or something. They
only found out afterwards that they were related and they signed the
שטר. shtar. Let's say they really intended to testify. Would you still
say it doesn't matter, we're going to still exclude the פסול pasul
testimony? Maybe you would. Maybe the nature of a שטר shtar is
that by definition if it's פסול, pasul, it never became part of
the שטר. shtar. Okay so I don't know, but it is a
strange הלכה halacha that we don't say נמצא אחד קרוב או פסול,
nimtza echad karov o pasul, certainly not in a normal case. Maybe
in the case I gave where everybody very intentionally wanted it it
would, but otherwise if you just have a פסול pasul thing you
exclude it. Now what I don't know is let's say you have
five signatures, two of them are brothers, which signature did you exclude?
Which brother, right? Is it like one of them is excluded but
not necessarily both? Let's say you had three, you couldn't exclude both.
Which one would you have excluded? Could be you don't know, like
it's Heisenberg's
uncertainty principle. We only have one brother's signature but we never know
which one. But like again it sort of shows some of the
problems here, but it's an amazing הלכה halacha and that allows you
to fill it up with עדים edim and for the שטר shtar
to still be כשר. kasher. Yes Dov, you had a question. Do
the עדים edim have to witness the שטר shtar at the same
time, the same place?
Yeah, so that's an interesting point.
Meaning let's say let's say they heard me, like I said to
you two, be my עדים edim that I borrowed, you know, a
thousand dollars from Eli. And then I said, you know, to John
Israel there, be my עדים edim that I borrowed a thousand dollars
from Eli. Could all four of you get together and write the
same שטר? shtar?
Probably, though that's a good question. So what's the relevance of that
question? Well that's maybe a way of looking at that differently than
physical than testimony in general which is people witness the same event
happening at the same time so when they're put together... Right, oh
so I see, the same right that is true. Part of what
defines a כת kat is not only they're coming to בית דין
beis din with the intent to testify
but they're actually having witnessed it with the intent to testify. And
that might also create a different type of an organization of the
group. That is definitely a possibility. Now I want to add two
things here about there's a whole long discussion in תוספות tosfos based
on other גמרות gemaras which is what do you think is worse
in terms of if we had to say תוספות tosfos has a
discussion maybe it's not always true that certain עדים edim are we
can ignore them. If you had to choose between if you had,
you know, if the פסול pasul עדים edim were here in the
or the פסול pasul עדים edim were here, right which ones would
you you know whether at the top or the bottom, which ones
do you think would be the easier ones to ignore? The middle
one.
Well middle, not top or bottom? The one on top. The top,
these. Why is that easier to ignore? Because you could say they
added it in. Because maybe they were added in to deal with
the white space. Okay there's a reason to say the bottom ones
are easier to ignore. First of all you could always just cut
off the שטר shtar here. These are the ones that are more
connected to the thing.
Right also because this was the I mean it's another way of
saying it but because this was like the critical zone that it
would have פסול pasul the שטר, shtar, you know this sort of
determines the כשרות kashrus of the שטר, shtar, this zone, right? So
you could have said the ones on the top are more important,
the ones on the bottom are less important. Also
but to support the idea that maybe the ones are on the
top are less, the בית דין's beis din sort of validation הנפק,
hanpek, you know whatever which should sort of say we validated the
things, would be on the bottom would be closer to the bottom
witnesses, right? It just would be at the bottom of the שטר.
shtar. So it more seems to be going on these. So anyway
so what so it's not clear which you would say. Based on
our סוגיה, sugya, right? The fact that we had to justify filling
in the space is okay with this whole סוכה sukkah analogy, it
sounds like here would be more of a reason to invalidate and
logically it is closer to the actual document. And even here פסול
pasul are okay. So if the כשר kasher ones are good
here and the פסול pasul ones are down here it would certainly
be okay. Okay so that's I think what we would naturally conclude
from the גמרא. gemara. I would naturally conclude it. Okay Eli's not
so certain. Well תוספות tosfos isn't so certain either. He goes back
and forth. The majority of תוספות tosfos assumes פסול pasul עדים edim
anywhere because חזקיה's chizkiyah statement or the not חזקיה chizkiyah the original
statement היו ארבעה וחמישה ונמצא אחד קרוב או פסול hayu arba v'chamisha
v'nimtza echad karov o pasul doesn't seem to matter where the פסול
pasul one is, right? I mean heck, let's say you had a
case where you had כשר פסול pasul. כשר *kasher pasul kasher*. You
didn't even have the two כשר *kasher* ones together. Could you eliminate
it? So the original statement sounds like yes, just eliminate anyone that's
not good. Okay, so that's תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*'s basic inclination, but at
one point תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* thinks based on a הלכות גדולות *Hilchos
Gedolos* or whatever, he goes back and forth and he says no,
maybe only if the כשר *kasher* ones... if the פסול pasul *pasul*
ones are on top is it okay. But let me restate that:
maybe only if the כשר *kasher* ones are on the bottom it's
okay. Okay? But if the כשר *kasher* ones are on top and
the פסול *pasul* are on bottom, he says maybe it's no good.
So תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* goes back and forth on that question. The
other question תוספות *Tosafot* goes back and forth on is, if you
notice, in the ברייתא *Braitah* it says נמצא קרוב או פסול *nimtza
karov o pasul*. חזקיה *Chizkiyah* just says קרובים *krovim*. What's the difference
between a קרוב *karov* and a פסול *pasul*? A קרוב *karov* is
a relative who otherwise would be כשר *kasher* on a different שטר
shtar *shtar*. He's just not כשר *kasher* here because he's related to
one of the עדים eidim *edim* or one of the parties. A
פסול *pasul* is somebody that would be פסול *pasul* on any שטר
shtar *shtar*. Okay? So תוספות *Tosafot* has a whole question about does
he mean only קרוב *karov*? Or does he mean לאו דווקא *lav
davka*, קרוב *karov* but it would include a case of פסול *pasul*?
And he's not so certain. Okay, now all of this sounds like
a nice theoretical discussion, except for the fact that the רמ"א Rama
*Rama* in הלכות כתובות *Hilchos Ksuvos* says that the practice was on
a כתובה Kesubah. *ksuva* to get a lot of relatives and whatnot
to sign the כתובה *ksuva* after the כשר עדים eidim *kasher edim*
have signed it because of this principle of like you know it
doesn't matter מילאוהו קרובים *miluhu krovim* and it was done as a
way of giving כיבודים *kibudim* of לכבוד חתן וכלה *likvod choson v'kallah*.
Let me actually see quickly if I can even find the רמ"א
*Rama*. Now this is relevant
because
in our modern
more egalitarian age I have been asked multiple times from a wide
range of different people about can we have women witnesses sign the
כתובה *ksuva* after the men sign it? Which is you know very
interesting, right? And in terms of תוספות *Tosafot*'s question of does it
matter קרוב *karov* or פסול *pasul*? So on the one hand you
might say oh a woman is פסול *pasul*, she's not a קרוב
*karov*. On the other hand, interestingly, there's a whole range of פוסקים
*poskim* that believe that the principle of נמצא אחד מהם קרוב או
פסול *nimtza echad meihem karov o pasul* doesn't apply to a woman.
Because if a man who's a קרוב *karov* is כשר *kasher* in
a different context, and a פסול *pasul* is פסול *pasul* like a
גזלן *gazlan* in every context, on the one hand you could say
a woman is not a כשר עד *kasher eid* so she's פסול
*pasul* in every context. On the other hand, most פוסקים *poskim* say
she's not a פסול עד *pasul eid*, she's not an עד *eid*.
Because at least a man who's a גזלן *gazlan*, right, could do
תשובה *teshuva* and then be a כשר עד *kasher eid*. So right
now he's invalid, but he's in the category. A woman is never
in the category so she's not a פסול עד *pasul eid*, so
she doesn't have any impact on the group. Okay, so it's very
interesting in terms of that. But this is the question, can we
basically... people don't even realize that they're asking this, they don't even
know about this רמ"א *Rama* or about this גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*, but
to some level what they're asking is can we like reinstitute this
practice to have you know people who are not the... after the
כשר עדים edim *kasher edim* sign, to have the other witnesses sign
it as well. So, what? Is there a preference for where they
sign it or...? So what I tell people to do, and I've
never done it as a מסדר *mesader*, but I've said if you're
going to do it what I would say you should do because
I said the following also and this gets to תוספות *Tosafot*'s point
about why you don't say נמצא אחד מהם קרוב או פסול *nimtza
echad meihem karov o pasul*. So if the reason you don't say
נמצא אחד מהם קרוב או פסול *nimtza echad meihem karov o pasul*
is because of the context that they're doing it to sign for
כבוד *kavod* and not לשם עדות *lesheim eidus*, I say in a
society in which
that phenomenon was known, that people sometimes would sign it just לכבוד
*likavod* and not לשם עדות *lesheim eidus*, you know, maybe it's an
easier way to assume that that context or the possibility of that
context segregates out that signature. But in the case where that's sort
of like never done, it's harder for me to sort of see
that you could just assume that that's the context of the signature.
So what I say, what I tell people if they want to...
what? You're going to say the opposite? Yeah, in the context where
clearly you're asking women to sign it because you enjoy that, you
want that, you want their... right, so you could say like in
this context like at your wedding. The question also... the question is
do you look at how it was signed when it was signed,
or do you look at what the שטר shtar *shtar* is saying?
In the context in which people understand that there are signatures that
might not be עדות *eidus* signatures, it's not making the... the שטר
shtar *shtar* is not making the same statement as in a context
where people never, you know, don't see it that way. Anyway, so
what I just tell people to do is after you have so-and-so
sign עד *eid* and so-and-so sign עד *eid*,
I tell them write a line like that says something like this:
וגם אנו חתמנו מטה לכבוד החתן והכלה *vegam anu chatamnu mata likvod
hachoson vehakallah*,
and then like we're also signing in honor of the חתן והכלה
*choson vehakallah*, and then just have their signing and I say don't
put the word עד *eid* afterwards. Okay, so that's what I tell
people who want to do it to do it, but it's actually
let me just see if I can quickly find... that רמ"א, okay,
and that's actually but it's actually quite fascinating that this is actually
like למעשה. L'ma'aseh. All right, I'm not finding it. I will look
I will get it to you tomorrow. I'll find it tomorrow. Send
me an email. But anyway, it is definitely the רמ"א records that
practice by a למעשה L'ma'aseh that's what they would do by a
כתובה. All right, let's keep on continuing in the גמרא. Gemara The
גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: איבעיא להו. Ibayu lehu. So after that fascinating discussion, we get
to a little more technical discussion. איבעיא להו: Ibayu lehu: שני שיטין
שאמרו, shenei shitin she'ameru, הן ואווירן, hen ve'aviran, או דילמא o dilma
הן ולא אווירן? hen velo aviran? So after we decided that it
was anything less than two was okay, we want to know what
defines two to make it פסול. Does it mean two with the
space between them or without the space between them? Okay, everybody understand
what that means? Right, if you've got a 12 point font, right,
and this is sort of the size of your lettering here, whatever,
and so this is a line, right, so your other line would
be here, right, that's where you would have sort of the writing,
and then there'd be like a little gap you'd have. So when
we say if it's two lines apart, you know, so that makes
it פסול because then somebody could fill in those two lines, right,
so presumably it would mean two lines plus the normal intervening space.
Or do we say no, maybe if it's exactly two lines
it's
okay
because somebody will write them without a space between them or will
write them a little smaller? Or do we say no, somebody's going
to do that, it'll be obvious that they squeezed it in, and
therefore it'll be clear that it was done after the fact. Okay,
so that's the question. Now
that
we
said
it's anything less
than
two
lines is okay because it'll be obvious it was squeezed in later,
what if it's exactly two lines and it doesn't include the intervening
space? All right. הן ואווירן, Hen ve'aviran, או דילמא o dilma הן
ולא אווירן. hen velo aviran. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak, נסתברא nistavera דהן ואווירן. dehen ve'aviran. No, it makes
sense that only when it's them with their intervening space. דאי סלקא
דעתך De'isalka daatach הן ולא אווירן, hen velo aviran, שיטה אחת בלא
אווירה shita achas belo avira למאי חזי? l'mai chazi? So what would
it be good without the space afterwards, meaning it's not the normal
way of writing. אלא שמע מינה Ela shema mina הן ואווירן, hen
ve'aviran, שמע מינה. shema mina. It must be only with the intervening
space, then it will look completely natural if somebody tries to squeeze
something in. רב חסדא Rav Chisda אמר משמיה דחזקיה: amar mishmei deChizkiyah:
שני שיטין שאמרו shenei shitin she'ameru בכתב יד עדים biksav yad eidim
ולא בכתב יד סופר. velo biksav yad sofer.
Let's say, you know, when you are a professional, so, you know,
your size of your lettering is a certain size and so on,
and whereas if you're a non-professional, you know, you're writing more script
and, you know, again it doesn't mean whose hand. Let's say, you
know, when you are a professional, so you know, your size of
your lettering is a certain size and so on, and whereas if
you're a non-professional, you know, you're writing more script and you know,
you're, again it doesn't mean whose handwriting it is, but it means
like what size of the lettering. Okay? So it says, since our
concern here is that you're going to squeeze in your own lines
and presumably it sounds like your script writing is bigger, right? You
understand that? Like if a סופר sofer is trained, they're able to,
like, you know, control their hands more and get the stuff to
be a more uniform and small size, whereas a normal script would
not be that way. So these two lines are only going to
be a problem if they're the height of your
normal person's script, which is a bigger size. If they're the height
of only a סופר sofer script, it's not, because the only way
you're going to get a סופר sofer script in there is by
having a סופר sofer add something after it's been signed, and a
סופר's sofer not going to agree to add something after it's been
signed. Of course you could say I don't get it, you have
a whole story by a סופר sofer and then you have something,
you know, in the, you know, in somebody else's handwriting in those
last two lines, isn't that an indication that it was forged? But,
you know, not necessarily, sometimes you could have the סופר sofer write
something and before we got the witnesses to sign it, we realized,
hey, wait, we had a discussion and we wanted to make an
emendation and we wrote it in before we got the witnesses to
sign. So it's possible that that happened without it being a forgery,
okay? So that in itself, the fact that it is just a
normal person's script is not doesn't prove it's a forgery, but we're
only concerned that that's what you're going to do. You're not going
to get a סופר sofer to put in those lines after it's
been signed. Okay? So he says בשני שיטים שעמו בכתב ידי עדים
ולא כתב יד סופר bishnei shitim she'imu bechtav yedei eidim velo ktav
yad sofer מאי טעמא mai ta'ama why? דכל המזייף לאו לגבי סופר
אזיל ומזייף dechol hamizayef lav legabei sofer azil umizayef if
you're going to forge it, meaning you're going to add lines after
it's been signed, you're not going to get the סופר sofer to
go ahead and do it, you're going to do it yourself.
וכמה vechama now, how much is actually these, like, two lines? I
mean we're going back and visiting this idea of, like, the space
between them with a little bit more precision. So אמר רב יצחק
בן אלעזר amar Rav Yitzchak ben Elazar כגון לך לך זה על
גבי זה kegon lach lach zeh al gabi zeh
one on top of the other, because if you think about the
two words לך lach right? So the למד lamed goes up and
if this is your normal height of a line, the למד lamed
actually demands an extra space, right, because of the way Hebrew is
written, right? And the כף chaf actually demands an extra space down
there. So when we say two lines, he's saying it means actually
two lines with the extra spaces for the raised letters and for
the lower letters, okay? So this is one line and this is
one אוויר avir and this is one אוויר, avir, okay? The airspace
below the line to get that, and if we have to allow
לך לך lach lach to be, maybe what I need to do
here is to draw it for you. What? To say לך לך.
lach lach. לך lach so if there's a word on one line,
it says and I'm giving לך lach this and this and this
and this and then I'm giving לך lach this, so if down
here I've got to get so the worst-case scenario is I would
have my word לך, lach, my second לך lach here, right, appear
here, right, which creates, right, you know, that possibility, right? So
okay, so that's one line,
here's one line, okay, here's another אוויר avir
and and plus, right, now I've got
because the עדים edim are going to be signing here, right, where
do the עדים edim sign?
Right, the point is how much space, here's the document above, how
much space do I have to leave so somebody could put in
two lines and it could look natural? That's the question, right? So
what it's saying is, is that for somebody to be able to
put in two lines and it look natural, you would need to
be able to write לך לך lach lach here, which would be
what would that be? That would be two lines and ארבעה אווירים.
arba'ah avirim.
Okay, anything less than that, it's not enough space to before we
said two lines and one אוויר avir between them, but now we're
realizing actually for it to fully look natural to stick in two
lines, you would need two lines and ארבעה אווירים. arba'ah avirim. Okay?
Natural to leave the אוויר avir in the middle? Yeah, so the
point is what you really could do is you could actually just
be careful the way you write, and if it happened like this,
you know, a good סופר sofer will just go like that, right?
Exactly, so תוספות has that discussion that maybe we don't need two
אווירים avirim here, the other thing is right, so תוספות has that
discussion, but this is the way the רשב"ם Rashbam reads it, okay?
So כגון לך
לך זה על גבי זה kegon lach lach zeh al gabi zeh
אמר קסבר שני שיטים וארבעה אווירים amar kasvar shnei shitim ve'arba'ah avirim
two lines and ארבעה אווירים. arba'ah avirim. רבי חייא
בר אמי משמיה דעולא אמר כגון למ"ד מלמעלה וכ"ף מלמטה. Rabbi Chiya
bar Ammi mishmei d'Ulla amar k'gon lamed mil'ma'alah v'chof mil'mata. You don't
have to assume they're constantly banging into one another. אמר קסבר שני
שיטין ושלש אוירים. amar kasavar shnei shitin v'shalosh avirim. You don't have
to assume that the height here is going to hit into there.
Basically you have to allow for the למ"ד lamed above and the
כ"ף chof below and just one normal space here between them. Okay,
because presumably this reason that you could always just you know adjust
this. Okay. ואבא
אמר כגון ברוך בן לוי בשיטה אחת, v'Abba amar k'gon Baruch ben
Levi b'shita achas, which is very ברוך Baruch has a כ"ף chof
and לוי Levi has a למ"ד. lamed. Okay.
קסבר שיטה אחת ושני אוירים, kasavar shita achas u'shnei avirim, which is
very strange because that seems to argue on a position before that
two lines. תוספות says okay maybe he disagrees. He says only one
line. All right, so now we have different variations though of what
this two-line measure is. אמר רב לא שנו אלא בין עדים לכתב.
amar Rav lo shanu ella bein edim l'chsav. אבל בין עדים לאשרתה
אפילו טובא נמי כשר. aval bein edim l'ashrasa afilu tu'v'nami kashar. So
this is the אשרתה. ashrasa. This is the קיום השטר. kiyum hashtar.
So if basically I've got my עדים eidem. up here right after
the without any white space under after it okay and then I've
got a lot of white space before the בית דין beis din
where the בית דין beis din would affix their קיום השטר, kiyum
hashtar, that's okay. All right, that's not a problem. Does now the
question is like where why? Maybe somebody will come ahead and write
oh by the way after they signed it we you know somebody's
going to insert in here we the בית דין beis din you
know saw that ראובן Reuven you know ראובן Reuven paid you know
paid you know half of the debt, half of the debt. Okay
and you stick that right before the בית דין's beis din קיום.
kiyum. Now of course you could say that the בית דין's beis
din קיום kiyum only means to validate the witnesses it should never
be interpreted to be validating anything else. The שטר shtar? ends here
but that maybe is well let's see what the גמרא Gemara says
because the גמרא Gemara is now going to say we don't have
to worry about a white space. Okay. אבל בין עדים לאשרתה אפילו
טובא נמי כשר. aval bein edim l'ashrasa afilu tu'v'nami kashar. Even a
lot of space. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי שנא בין עדים
לכתב? mai shena bein edim l'chsav? דילמא מזייף וכתב מאי דבעי. dilma
mezaief v'chosav mai d'va'ei. Why is there a problem between עדים eidem
and the document? Because you'll forge and write something in the white
space so
and you'll have the signatures of the witnesses going on it. בין
עדים לאשרתה נמי. bein edim l'ashrasa nami. If you leave a white
space between the עדים and the קיום, kiyum, מזייף וכתב מאי דבעי
mezaief v'chosav mai d'va'ei
you'll write fit through what you want וחתימי סהדי v'chasimi sa'adi and
the witnesses. Well I mean the בית דין beis din signatures will
be essentially validating that. Okay so how does that work? So the
גמרא Gemara says דמטייט ליה. d'mitayeit lei.
No because what you do is you sort of like messy it
up. Meaning what you do is is that after they did this
what בית דין beis din would do is is they would just
put like you know marks here you know just like marks like
that you know no signature whatever no text. So that marks would
basically make that space unusable which signal you know so and presumably
if somebody I don't know would like scrape that away and write
something it would be obvious it had been erased. So that makes
this space unusable so we're not afraid that it'll be filled in
with anything. So the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי ee hachi so
do the same up here. Just do that and make a קיום
השטר. kiyum hashtar. Also why why not just validate it
up above? Yeah I don't know maybe that's the way you would
do it. Like I don't know if you've ever you know if
you've ever stood to see a whatever you know a notary public
they always but that's I think because of their their machine only
goes at the bottom but I don't know why they wouldn't do
it higher I can't explain that. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says
אי הכי בין עדים לשטר נמי לטייט ליה. ee hachi bein edim
l'shtar nami l'itayeit lei. So why don't you just sort of like
smudge that area and that'll solve that problem too. אמרי לא סהדי
אטיותא הוא דחתימי. amri no sa'adi atiyusa hu d'chasimi. So no because
people will say that the witnesses are signing meaning people will say
oh so if you've got this smudge stuff here the signatures aren't
going on the שטר above that says ראובן Reuven owes $100 they're
signing on a I don't know you did some nice design like
imagine someone also does you know some curly cues or whatever you
know whatever they do something like that you know they do some
nice design and they say yeah this is part of the witnesses
are signing how much they like the design which is a strange
idea what does it mean to sign something that isn't words? But
once there's something else that essentially what it's saying is is that
it means that the signatures witnesses are not relating to the שטר
above. If that's true says the גמרא Gemara saying here say the
בית דין's beis din קיום kiyum isn't relating to the שטר above.
So the גמרא Gemara says
so
בין עדים לאשרתה נמי bein edim l'ashrasa nami so if you put
this design or the smudges between the witnesses and the קיום kiyum
אמרי בי דינא אטיותא הוא דחתימי. amri beis dina atiyusa hu d'chasimi.
They're just signing their signatures on the design and not on the
עדים. So גמרא says no, בדינא תיוותא לא חתימי. bedina tiyuta lo
chasimi. Nobody's going to think that, it's understood that a קיום kiyum
only relates to signatures. So I don't, I mean it's bizarre, and
signatures relate to a design, they don't relate to a שטר? It
doesn't make sense. Why anyway, why don't we just say that, so,
whatever it is, I have no answer, there's a lot of questions
here. Why don't they sign it higher? Why don't we say the
קיום kiyum only refers to עדים and even if there was words
written here it wouldn't relate to it? I don't know the answer
to any of that. But the basic point is we do not
allow white space here. It either has to be כתב ktav or
it has to be filled in with עינם, einam, like we said
before, you can fill it in with עינם einam but you can't
fill it in with smudges or designs. Here you can make a
distance if you fill it in with some type of a smudges.
Okay, and we will, so we'll pick up with this tomorrow and
I will try to have for you that רמ״א Rema tomorrow that
says that that's what they do by.